[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so Poland has a widespread view that you can choose between a pleasant path to awakening and unpleasant one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant usually means through brahma viharas and unpleasant means through raw insight like contemplation of impermanence, sickness and death and ananta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we really have a choice in this regard.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where does the view come from?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where does it come from?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is the Polish early Buddhism society, for example, which promotes this view?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but I mean, where did they get it from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, did they come up with it or is it sort of based on suttas or something?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's based partially on suttas and it's based partially on commentaries.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, putting commentaries aside, as one should,
[SPEAKER_01]: The suttas that talk about those different forms of practice are the... suttas refer to sotāpānas, at least.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not just somebody can just choose how they're gonna walk the path that the Buddha outlined for someone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it starts with somebody who already has the right view, who already knows what nibbāna is,
[SPEAKER_01]: Who already sees their own mind, because one of the prerequisites for sotāpārthi is developing of citta nimitta, seeing the signs and features of the mind for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, in the process of taming their mind, that process might be pleasant, unpleasant, might be quick and unpleasant, might be slow and unpleasant, and all those different permutations.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not something one can choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: All one can choose is whether they're going to tame the mind or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... what path you're going to be walking can only be known in hindsight after you walked it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say, oh, actually, that wasn't too bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eh... because if it's a matter of choice, why would anybody choose the unpleasant path?
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody would choose the quick and pleasant, if it's actually a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, there would be only one way to enlightenment that everybody would choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody in their right mind would want to choose suffering for a long time towards the enlightenment, if there is an option.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how about putujanas?
[SPEAKER_01]: Putujanas have no choice whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't see the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they're putujanas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, them choosing what path they follow is just choosing their own abstract ideas of what they think the Buddha might have been teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not seeing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's kind of the main point there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why such suttas, they do talk about those different aspects, different emphasis of the practice, or refer to somebody who already sees what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not just that Pūtūjana doesn't have a choice, he doesn't even see the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the sole practice of Pūtūjana should be establishing himself in virtue, recollecting the right themes, the right context, so to... the mind to come up, so that they can see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's kind of the beginning of the right practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's most likely not going to feel pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, like, sure, it depends on an individual.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the other suttas say, it depends on how much dust a person has in their eyes to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: But generally speaking, today, already dhamma is on like a decline.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's been like two and a half millennia since the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lots of splits, lots of different views, lots of different opinions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not hearing the true dhamma when you hear the dhamma today.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's highly unlikely you'll be hearing the actual dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've got to be sieving through stuff, working through things, digging through to kind of discern what the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means that most of people today, most of us, probably have a lot more dust in our eyes, because if we didn't, we would have already been enlightened in the Buddhist time, or shortly afterwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, it's like, you have an option to establish yourself in virtue, to recognize that mind, the wild animal, to train it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How's that gonna be felt?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's important to you, before you even start taming the animal,
[SPEAKER_01]: How it's going to be felt means you're not going to be taming the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's like, oh, I'll train this this dog only if it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you don't really care about the outcome of the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your first and foremost priority is your own pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you're putujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: So everybody that still wants to choose their own path, for that very reason, they won't be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they're refusing to give up their emotional dependence on pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And do brahmavihāras can help putujanas to... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can they help?
[SPEAKER_01]: The very first brahmavihāra starts by practicing the framework of non-ill will towards your own mind, towards your own citta, protecting the citta, the boundless mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't even see the citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can they practice that which only begins by seeing the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so as I understand, currently, practice of metta is used as kind of painkiller for people...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, management.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, you don't need the Buddhas for that, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha's teaching for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just lots of, lots of other technique, methods, wishful thinking, contemplations, visualizations can help you with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: To an extent, but it will not uproot the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only the dhamma can actually approve the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for that, you need to aim for that, not just use it as management, or for cover-up and sort of making yourself feel better when things are bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can it be helpful for people to use this kind of metta as management?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not the metta they're using.
[SPEAKER_01]: Metta begins when you see the citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't see the citta, there is no practice of Brahma Vihāras for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever you do, can help or not, it's not the Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we shouldn't be calling meta.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, we shouldn't be calling such similar practices that people refer to as jhānas, that are not based on renunciation and seeing their mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also not jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, this is not meta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, regular meditation like ānāpānasati and brahma-mihāras are for sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, hi, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all of the... any meditation in the suttas, which are really like practices of composures and calming of that animal, requires you to see the animal, requires you to clearly discern the mind for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you do so, you'll be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're trying to calm something that you don't see.
[SPEAKER_00]: It makes no sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... regular people, can they do contemplations like contemplation of death, contemplation of sickness, contemplation of anatta?
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's, that's, that's what they should be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what everybody should be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you're a layperson or then later a monk, those contemplations remain the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just probably how much time and
[SPEAKER_01]: The quality of your effort changes, like, you know, as you change the environment into more secluded and monastic and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the contemplations remain the same, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, if as a lay person you start contemplating those things without also establishing yourself in virtue, you're probably going to experience a lot of disturbances internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're kind of undermining everything your current household life depends on, and you don't really have the means of virtuous behavior providing container for your mind when it gets disturbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, it's probably better to actually, first and foremost, start paying attention to your behavior, to your speech, what kind of topics and themes and thoughts you choose to dwell on during the day,
[SPEAKER_01]: Make sure it's not unwholesome, do the best of your efforts, and then also, bit by bit, start increasing these contemplations that will undermine your sense of self, your sense of ownership, and all of that, which is sickness, aging, death, change, things that are dear to you, things that you find safety in.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are otherwise already, basically, by not being in your control, by not being able to do anything about them changing, if the change were to occur.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so I... basically, to make yourself safe, you need to first practice virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you need to practice the virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, you can take it on in that religious, dutiful sense, but you actually need to train in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by that, as we spoke so many times in other talks, means, like, those principles behind the precepts, you need to not just adhere to them externally, but also internally, when it comes to you choosing the reasons for saying things, for speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Make sure it doesn't come out of those same principles of unwholesome, they were against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, same about you, when it comes to your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, you might not be killing anybody but your body, but do you wish harm mentally?
[SPEAKER_01]: And do you allow, do you allow those thoughts to proliferate?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you fuel them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you accept them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do you say, when they present themselves through the angry mind, you say, no, I won't allow these thoughts to occupy me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's, that's already a training effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will not come automatically on its own, simply by you keeping the precepts externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person needs to train in virtue, to become established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can management technique help in this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, failing to practice rightly, it's already a form of management.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're not... you're not... you're not going to overnight stop managing and suddenly be on the right path immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether you want it or not, you will be managing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is, when you start confusing the management for the practice, for the uprooting, that's when you're going to stop progressing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're still aiming at the actual uprooting, at the actual immovability, at the actual completely being untouched by the suffering,
[SPEAKER_01]: That aim, as it's being developed, is providing a form of management.
[SPEAKER_01]: Up until it's developed, when it's developed, when you uprooted it, then you don't need to manage.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I tell you, yeah, management is fine, means any idea that you find helpful, you're going to start confusing that for practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think, I am progressing towards sotāpatti through doing random stuff that makes me feel better when I suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's absolutely not the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you need to aim at the uprooting.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the process of that aim and developing that aim, improving that aim, you will be managing one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, maybe, is it good to learn some management techniques first?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: If I just said, aiming at the uprooting of suffering will provide you with management.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Learning techniques first, it's probably gonna then carry a high risk of being confused for practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're gonna find it helpful, but it's not actually aiming at uprooting, so it stops there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Aiming at uprooting, you will also find helpful, and it actually aims at the uprooting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is practicing virtue and sense restraint uprooting the suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, if you start applying it on all these three levels, body, speech and mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: And taking responsibility not just for what you do, what you say, but also what you choose to think and revolve around during the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: And make the effort to not do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, oh, I'm thinking angry thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, the mind is coming up, the mind's coming, oh, let me just go and concentrate, calm down, watch my nostrils, do this or that, for it to go away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure, do that, but you haven't aimed at the uprooting of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you manage the problem after it came up, but you haven't understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can that problem not come up in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, when you have these thoughts pressuring you, yes, you shouldn't be giving in, in accepting those thoughts and fueling them further, but at the same time, you shouldn't be trying to get rid of that state of mind, because you need to understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you just want to manage it away, because it's unpleasant, you're not going to understand anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's that training.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you sense restraint, and when you watch yourself, how you react on this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, you practice sense restraint, and your mind is going to start... your mind is going to start to complain, resist, increase the pressure, and you don't lose the sight of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to watch yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to watch that background where your mind is, and what pressures it come up with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, make sure that you're not just blindly trying to get rid of the discomfort of that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what people always confuse.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not seeing the mind, they identify the discomfort that the mind puts on them, with the thoughts that revolve around their day-to-day kind of attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, they're like, oh, if I stop thinking, I want to stop thinking so that the pain in the background goes away, so that the mind stops hurting.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's too much now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to not proliferate those thoughts, but you don't want to get rid of or try... Well, you can't get rid of.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just going to be covering it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't want to deny the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to know it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: As Satipaṭṭhāna Sutta says, he knows the lustful mind as lustful mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't say he replaces it with another better mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, he knows it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The knowledge is the freedom from the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows the angry mind as angry mind, elated mind as elated
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's also what... what... the more you know it, the more... the less identification you're going to have with that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you just see it in its own state for what it is, and you... you didn't make it that way, and you see it coming and going in a certain way, has nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wasn't there a sutta that you can replace your thoughts, like, eh... bad pieces of... Yeah, but it wasn't about the replacement of the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was exactly what I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it was like, when you are pressured towards central thoughts, you don't give in to central thoughts, and you can think asubha for your citta, not for replacement of the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, every of those five ways of becoming a master of your thought, is the threshold, the reference point for that, is the state of citta behind it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can replace the thoughts, as long as your replacement of the thoughts is not trying to get rid of the state of the mind, which is what everybody does.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they want to stop thinking, that's why we want to think positive thoughts, because the mind hurts, and they refuse to accept that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why are you replacing defaults?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you're not replacing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're simply not giving attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, when I say a lustful object presents itself, you can choose to see the beautiful or ugly aspects of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people by default choose the beautiful, but then they were told, oh, that's bad, you shouldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, they want to force the ugly aspects to get rid of that state of mind, because it hurts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that will not bring any understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the choice presents itself to think beautiful aspects of ugly aspects out of a central mind, you don't try to get rid of the central mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just make sure you look at the ugly aspects of the same experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how the mind learns that the thing that... that the things that the mind is attracted to are actually disgusting.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to bring new things, a new state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want, within the same state, to teach it rightly, to show it the different aspect of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why that sutta, again, does not apply to anybody randomly, putujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, at the end of the sutta, if you develop those five ways of thinking, you'll be an arahant without anything left to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's a lot more, and certainly a lot subtler than just, oh, when it's this thought, think the opposite, because anybody can do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uneducated, completely sort of random, not familiar with Buddhists can do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing there to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just stick to do the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just look at the ugly when it's this, look at that when it's that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the whole nuance of the state of mind that's bound by both and presenting the right aspect to it, that's completely gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: That people don't see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why that sutta is one of the most misunderstood ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at it, it's specifically, every one of those refers to the citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does not just refer to just think this or that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the citta is lustful, within the lustful mind, you presented the aspects of the same thing that are disgusting.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the citta is angry, within that angry mind, you don't just choke it and beat it to stop being angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Show it the nice aspects, the neutral aspects, the friendly aspects of the same thing that it hates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you might still have a desire for that citta to change, but if you don't give in that blind forcing of change into citta because it hurts, just present it the aspect and wait.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's something like you have to endure the mind on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind will not immediately lose the desire when you present it, say, with the ugly aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be push... it will be pushing for the beautiful aspects.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind will not immediately overcome hate, if you present it with the friendly aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be pushing for the hateful aspects, but you don't give in to the hateful aspects, you don't choose to proliferate them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, those thoughts are there, but you're not allowing them the center stage, as I say.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, bring the friendliness aspect, but again, not forcefully, to like, choke the mind with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just bring it up and leave it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what the mind is seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't want to see it, but you're forcing it to see it, by simply holding it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you stop when the mind sits down and loses anger, or when the mind calms down and loses passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, see, now, you didn't beat the passion, you didn't strangle the mind, you didn't try to kind of forcefully get out of it, get it out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You simply presented it the different aspect of the same thing, and the mind on its own sat down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And lost the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the animal for itself, so, oh, this is ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can be telling, repeating mantra in your head all you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Asubha, asubha, ugly, ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind doesn't see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind still sees the beautiful aspects, because that's the only thing you've been showing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whenever you think about asubha, you don't think about it presenting the ugly to that state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want the ugly to replace the whole experience of that mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why asubha doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might give you the shock value initially, and you will feel disenchanted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do it two or three times in that... wrongly, like how I just described, and the mind will find the attractive within the ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is no end to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you read the vinaya stories, there were cases of monks that they did sexual things with corpses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because they were perverted from the start, but because the asubha was not rooted rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind always can find beautiful even in the ugliest, and vice versa.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could find the ugliest in beautiful, in the most beautiful, if that's what you look for.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not using the mind as that reference which need to be taught these things, people then just try to replace one with the other, and mind will just pick and choose within the ugly what it likes, and the attraction will remain and come back on the top, and then you might even act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say, I am a regular person, I suffer a lot, and, like, my level of suffering is barely enabling me to function, and then I hear that during the road to the right view, I'm gonna suffer even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can I decide going that road?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you want to be free from suffering,
[SPEAKER_01]: You would do anything that takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody says, yeah, freedom from your ailment is this absolutely horrible, painful, bitter medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you really want to be healthy, you would take it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how bad it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't want to take it because it's bitter, means you don't really want to cure yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I don't like the taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, taste is more important to you than being free from pain, from suffering, from dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's your choice, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the hard part of this is that some teachers offer us the pleasant path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but as I said before, I mean, it doesn't take great intellect or supreme wisdom
[SPEAKER_01]: Anybody in this, who's been, like, say, for a few years on this earth, so to speak, can ask themselves, on the basis of the limited experience of a household's ordinary average life, things that are easy to get, things that are just smooth sailing and very, very, very quickly, pleasantly achieved,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or things that are hard to get, that you have to work for, endure, really put in effort, which of those things are usually more valuable, more long-lasting and have greater impact?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everybody knows an answer to that, the answer to that question.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddhist practice is no exception to that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: If anything, it's even more of that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because freedom from suffering, obviously, it's the most important fundamental thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's certainly not going to be easy sailing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the practice remains the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even when those pleasant parts were described in the suttas, they were not different parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were the same parts that just, for some people, were not as unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not something you can pre-decide.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason that those paths were not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I were to become celibate tomorrow, that's the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I suffer, will I suffer or will I not suffer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you will suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're the type that needs the suffering path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just set yourself with the right path from the suttas, and see if your mind resists or not, and that will... then you can tell which category you will fall in.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there were people back in the day, they just said, oh, yeah, this is unsuitable for me to engage in sexual intercourse, or it's unsuitable for me to do these things, and they abandoned it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And obviously, the mind didn't even suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, probably, most of those people were done by now.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would have already completed their work, if they had that little dust in their eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, maybe, as I said before, maybe you are the lucky one, maybe you really have little dust in your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Set yourself with the eight precepts, commit to the path, and see, if your mind doesn't suffer, great, you are the one who is on the pleasant path.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this whole idea of, oh, pleasant path is what I choose to do pleasantly for the Enlightenment, that's absolutely ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: The path is the same, unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people will suffer a lot on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people will suffer not so much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people won't suffer at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the path remains the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people will have to walk a long time the same path, do the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people not so long.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people can do it very quickly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the path is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and some people say that, for example, abandoning romantic relationships are spiritual bypassing because you are doing it out of fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Well, obviously, those people are not concerned about their own well-being and being free from suffering and saṃsāra, so it's not much to say to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they think spiritual relation... romantic relationships are a path, well, good luck to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, your usual logic goes like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you cannot abandon things if you really fear them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to, like, abandon fear first and, like, engage with it, so you can prove yourself that you can engage without fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: That does not seem very logical.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the sole reason you wouldn't be abandoning those things is because of fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you abandon fear if you just keep giving in to fear and supporting it and fueling it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ask yourself, which is more frightening?
[SPEAKER_01]: To continue romantic relationship or to break old ties and live alone?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is scarier?
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess it depends on the people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything depends on the individuals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not everybody starts from the same position.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, the practice and the principles remain unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is fear a good motivator to abandon the world?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, if it's obviously recognized rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you should have fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should be afraid of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should be afraid of liability to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, a young man basically recognizes that his situation, like, oh, I am prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, even if nothing
[SPEAKER_01]: Unpleasant is happening now.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that it could, shows that, oh, you are within the domain of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are its prey.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering will get you at some point.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that in itself, recognition, is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you develop fear towards that liability, then you will be practicing rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what would be the case with someone who, let's say, wants to have a romantic relationship from one side, and from the other side, he is afraid of them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he needs to make a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to have a romantic relationship, find safety in connecting with others, like in the world, you can do that, but you can't practice the dhamma at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's either-or.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ask yourself, which is more important?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which has greater impact?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one of those two offers a temporary, superficial sense of safety?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one of those two offers a lasting sense of safety?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when you free from saṃsara, develop right view, you do it once and for all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ask yourself those questions, think about them, and then make a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody forces you to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody forces you to do anything.